<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication of an injured lady written by the Lady Francesca Maria Lucretia Plunkett, one of the ladies of the privy chamber of the queen-mother of England.</title>
            <author>Loftus, Dudley, 1619-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2829A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475105</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2251:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication of an injured lady written by the Lady Francesca Maria Lucretia Plunkett, one of the ladies of the privy chamber of the queen-mother of England.</title>
                  <author>Loftus, Dudley, 1619-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Dudley Loftus--Cf. Wing (2nd ed.) and DNB, v. 12, p. 80.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 27: Frances Plunkett.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Lettera estortatoria--Cf. Wing (2nd ed.) and DNB.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 27.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained; t.p. torn, with loss of publisher name and date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plunkett, Francesca Maria Lucretia.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VINDICATION OF AN Injured Lady.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by the Lady</hi> FRANCESCA MARIA LUCRETIA PLUNKETT One of the LADIES of the Privy Chamber To the QUEEN-MOTHER of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151237:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151237:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I ſhall never take delight in being reckoned amongſt the <hi>Gaſte papiers</hi> or Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of this Age, yet I am at this time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by a more then ordinary neceſſity for the defence of my innocency, to make uſe of a known Right, that Cuſtome, the practice of time, hath allowed, even from the date of Learning, which is by a modeſt Anſwer in writing, to confute the calumnies and petulant reproaches of envious Adverſaries; <hi>Ad exempla igitur rev<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>camus, &amp; majorum vobis aſſerimus Conſuetudinem.</hi> Upon which ground I ſhall proceed to my Vindication, by the Readers favour, without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of fear to be taxed with a proud or ſelf conceited ſingularity, hoping it will not be accounted a reaſonleſs imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in me, if I follow the example of many prudent and vertuous Ladies, in a moderate defence void of paſſion and uncharitableneſs, and that my Adverſaries are not ſo incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, but that they may be amended with the lenitives of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber language, without the help of more operative Remedies; for having once cleared my ſelf to the world, I ſhall not ſo much ſeek their puniſhment, as reformation, and ſhall take leſs pleaſure in ſtriking them with a rod of Palms, then in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording them undeſerved gentleneſs; for I ſhall alwayes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of that noble <hi>Italian</hi>'s judgement who ſaith, <hi>La forza di chi vince è Coſa human ma laclemenza di chipardona è Coſa di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina.</hi> Though my Adverſaries be of the ſharpeſt and moſt cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous ſex, and are like the Placentine Advocates, <hi>Qui adeo (ut dicitur) ſubtili pollent ingenio, ut judicibus ipſis facile tenebras offundant,</hi> I would paſs them by with that regardleſs neglect which uſually ſtifles their contumely, were not the too facil credulity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151237:3"/> of ſome heavy-headed perſons, who are apt prodigally to throw away their belief on weak ſuggeſtions, greater then their ſubtilty; but it being in this reſpect a neceſſary duty, and for that no duty is more ſtringent to a perſon of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and generous ſentiments, then the defence of reputation; for, <hi>Qui famam negligit, dicitur crudelis</hi> ſaith the Canoniſt. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Expedit mihi magis mori, quàm ut gloriam meam quis evacuct.</hi> For theſe reaſons premiſed, I am reſolved to clear my ſelf beyond their oppoſition, and the doubts of all others in the world, to ſuch as in the peruſal hereof will make uſe of their judgement and reaſon, and in my progreſs I ſhall not let looſe the reins of reaſon at paſſions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, though I am provoked above imagination by thoſe women, to reſent their injuries done unto me at the higheſt rate, which are greater then any others I finde within the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry of my obſervation, remembrance or reading, to have been placed on a Lady of quality, by any perſons of worthy ſtate or condition, and therefore might have almoſt legitima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted impatience.</p>
            <p>But to make my entrance into this undertaking the more perſpicuous, I ſhall premiſe, as a proper <hi>adalantado,</hi> a few conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, worthy, as I humbly conceive, to be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I have not heard that any one man whoſoever, nor any woman that is acquainted with me, hath ſpoken any one word to my prejudice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe women who have opened their black mouths, or ſhewed their bad teeth againſt me, are onely thoſe few who are noted for their meeting oftentimes at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain places to none of the beſt purpoſes, as I conceive, and ſuch as either would hold up the repute of their leſſined vertues, or decayed beauties, by crying them down in others, as if they could reſtore irreparables in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151237:3"/> by endeavouring to deprive others of them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As they do not pretend to have ſo much acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with me, as thereby to obſerve any thing of my deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to juſtifie the character they have given of me, ſo have they not to this day named any one perſon to be their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer againſt me.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Of the many things uttered by them to my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, there is not any one, ſo much as in one inſtance of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple verified.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Thoſe women who know me not, like Sorcerers, who caſt a miſt upon the brighteſt morning, darkly and falſly inſinuate againſt me in doubtful terms, thoſe things which they dare not expreſs or declare againſt me; for, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ub aequivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationibus latens Calumnia, lae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it tutiſsime.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, There is nothing that they have uttered againſt me in the particulars hereafter mentioned, but have and will be refuted by the irrefragable teſtimony of thoſe perſons of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit who know me, and will ſpeak plainly without the allay of intereſt, and with great reaſon in my vindication, uſing no other arguments then ſuch as are drawn from the chief induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of belief.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Thoſe Ladies are not ſo learned, nor ſo wiſe, nor ſo noted for ſpeaking truth, as that their aſſertions can pretend to the dignity of Axioms.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, No Magiſtrate or Perſon of Honour hath given any ſhadow of juſtication, or afforded the leaſt colour of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to their proceedings againſt me, but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry have wondered thereat, not without diſtaſt and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Theſe Obſervations premiſed, I am now ready to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my furious Adverſaries in the very front of oppoſition, with purpoſe to refell every of their conſiderable Objections,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151237:4"/> whereof, if any ſhall happen to be unanſwered, I deſire it may be attribu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed rather to the weakneſs of my memory, then their ſtrength. As for ſome of their leſſer Objections, I ſhall omit to mention them here, either out of compaſſion to their ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, or of contempt of their weakneſſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe Ladies, in the firſt place, with intent to juſtifie the reſt of their ſucceeding injuries, and to give credit to what ill reports may eaſily be believed on that account, have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly reported me to be a Stage-player, but without any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of proof. I have read, that when no proof is offered of an Objection, then a ſimple Denial is Solution enough. Yet for Anſwer hereunto, I ſay, that were I a Stage-player, or ſo great a Player at Dice, as ſome of thoſe Ladies are, or an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainer of ſuch as uſe that game, I could not wonder that they ſhould be thereby animated with hopes of impunity, to endeavour prejudice to my reputation by never ſo notorious falſhoods; for I have obſerved within the view I have taken of the Civil Law (whereunto, as alſo unto the moſt eminent Profeſſors thereof, and particularly to one above the reſt, I do and ſhall alwayes bear a great reſpect) that <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorum ſuſceptoribus injuria damnumque datur impune.</hi> But foraſmuch as I am not ſo Theatrical as ſome of thoſe Ladies are, who frequently ſpend the time in the Play-houſe, which the affairs of their houſhould, or the exerciſe of Devotion might have more reaſonably and more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly imployed elſewhere, and that they fail in the very art of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring me lawfully, nor did I ever in my life tread on a Stage, nor was I ever acquainted with, or allied to any Stage-play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or ſo much as a Goſſip to any of them, nor am I by Law, Quality or diſpoſition of mind liable to ſuſtain injuries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due reſentments in my ſelf, or the endeavour of having due puniſhment inflicted upon the Authours of them. I ſhall give theſe Ladies to underſtand, that though I have hitherto
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151237:4"/> proceeded as leiſurely, as the Knights of the Band are to walk by the Rules of their Order, that juſtice to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred ſhortly againſt them, as reporters of falſe news, will free me from this their lying imputation, and make them ſuſpected in what they ſhall report hereafter againſt me. This I ſhall be forc't unto in due time, for to ſpare them too long in a caſe of this nature, would be a criminal indulgence, and a ſhrinking from the due maintenance of my Honour, which I am bound to uphold. In the mean time I ſhall leave it to the ſilent admiration of all ſober perſons, how that any fancy could be ſo wilde, as to think the world can be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to believe, that a perſon of a generous Education and Condition, ſhould turn a Stage-player, they ſhould, to have made their ſtories more currant, have imitated <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> who though a fabulous Writer, as <hi>Bochartus</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>Conatur tamen ſcribere vero quam ſimillima.</hi> They ſhould firſt of all have perſwaded the wo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld, that I was not deſcended from, nor allied to the moſt Honourable and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Family <hi>de la Torre</hi> in <hi>Venice,</hi> and to the Noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Genoua,</hi> where my Mother yet lives in an opulent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, being the Wife of one of the States of <hi>Genoua,</hi> or that I had leſs to my Portion then three or four thouſand pounds, which ſumme I brought in Marriage to my Husband, who is the Son of an ancient Noble man, and none of the lateſt Earls of this Kingdom, or that we were deſtitute of means to ſupport our Quality and Degree, all which if they had done, they might have had more hopes to be believed; But ſome gueſs, their purpoſes were to gratifie the Genius of this City of <hi>Dublin</hi> with ſome report of News, though never ſo foreign from Truth, as thinking perhaps it was, as <hi>Guildas</hi> ſayes of <hi>England</hi> in his time, <hi>Semper aliquid audire volens.</hi> Laſtly, ſome of thoſe who have been too buſie in inventing or reciting this calumny, have at laſt ſo much ingenuity to acknowledg, that I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151237:5"/> am not guilty thereof. This Calumny therefore which was laid on me, as an argument to induce the belief of other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, having loſt its force by a total evacuation, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhatter the whole ſuperſtructure, with confidence, that my Reader will allow reaſon in matters of this nature to be the Grand Patron of belief, and that the lowdneſs of an ungrounded clamour ought not to prevail againſt the calm reaſon of a modeſt anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. In the next place it is objected againſt me by thoſe Ladies, That a certain Learned Perſon is civilly treated by me when he comes to viſit me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer hereunto, I ſay, That the malice of thoſe Ladies (for ſo they would all be called) is as friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to me in effect, as it was miſchievous in their intentions, inſomuch, that their detraction ſeems as it were ſuborn'd to commend their enemy; for it hereby rather proves me civil, then convinces either of us guilty of ſin. But, if in their way of reaſoning, they will infer from the admittance of civil Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits an inclination to, or guiltineſs of immodeſty, I muſt needs ſay, that according to my Logick, which is as artificial as theirs, it is a too violent and forc'd conſequence, unleſs they will confeſs, that the much more frequent viſits which they receive daily from younger Gentlemen, and of leſs ſtrict be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, may render themſelves juſtly ſuſpected of what they would ſeem to charge me with. Again, I appeal to ſeveral of the ſaid Ladies, whether the ſame Gentleman hath not been admitted to as private familiarities, and frequent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them as ever he had with me. In the next place, I ſhall refer the Conſideration hereof to the whole City and Kingdom, where he hath ſhined from his infancy hitherto, as an Illuſtrious Example of refined morality, and an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gravity, which hath rendred his Company alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the graveſt and moſt vertuous of both Sexes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151237:5"/> whereſoever he reſided. And wherefore I ſhould be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Heteroclite in moralitie, by conforming to the rule and example of the Beſt, I ſhall leave to the admiration of all judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſons, whoſe ears are not ſtufft with obſtructive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, who will eaſily pronounce, that this argument is as light as the breath that framed it. Much more may be ſaid in Anſwer hereunto, but having ſaid ſo much already, I ſhall reſolve againſt needleſs amplifications, which are but teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of oſtentation, or at the moſt but expletives to fill up the place of arguments. I ſhall onely add this Conſideration, That theſe Ladies ſeal their own doings with the Signature of approbation, and brand mine with a mark of diſlike, whilſt we do the very ſame things, which I cannot conceive to be agreeable to the rules of decency, of civil deportment, or of juſtice: for though they be ſtiled a Convention, they have not authority ſufficient to bring their judgement into credit againſt this tranſcendant rule of Nature, <hi>Quod tibi fieri non vis, alteri ne feceris;</hi> for their juriſdiction being but a uſurpation, it is as incompetent as their debates have been impertinent. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, where the judgement of a Court is covered with the veil of a black hood, it is no wonder if the Sentence be erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous.</p>
            <p>The next Objection againſt me, is, That I have practiſed witchcraft to gain ſome ends on the Perſon above-mentioned. I ſhould look upon this Objection as a matter of infinite amazement, were I not aſſured that it proceeded onely from the fancy of them, who uſe to be afflicted with their own dreams, as taking them for divine advertiſements, and who are daily troubled with <hi>Chimera's,</hi> like thoſe of the <hi>Allum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bradoes</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> which have no beeing but in the monſtrous compoſition of wilde and diſtempered brains, infected with a diabolical malice and envy, which by ſingularity of deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, is called the Sin of the Devil.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151237:6"/>
            <p>It is my happineſs, and I heartily render thanks to God for it, all ears that have heard this report are not ſo credulous, as the tongues of that buiſie Siſterhood are licentious; yet I ſhall nevertheleſs ſay ſomething in anſwer to this Objection, whereby it will appear, that I am rather <hi>miſ randa,</hi> to be piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for being cauſleſly loaded with prophane calumny, then <hi>crubeſcenda,</hi> to be put to ſhame, for any thing of guilt they can truly charge upon me of this kinde. And let the world fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt judge, according to its common apprehenſion of things, whether moſt of my Adverſaries have not more likely fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their faces of ſuch infernal intelligencers, and more Signatures of wrinkled Old Age, the moſt uſual characteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks of Witches, then any they can diſcern in me, who have not yet compleated the 24th. year of my Age. This premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the conſideration of the world, I ſhall now write a wotd or two by way of Introduction to the underſtanding of the nature of Magick and Witchcraft, though I ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the ability of handling it learnedly; for, <hi>Magus quo peritior, eo deteſtabilior,</hi> which done, I ſhall ente<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a more perſpicuous path for the clearing of my ſelf briefly, without bringing my Self or the Readers into the circles of tedious Diſcourſes. As for Magick, and all other Arts of that perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious kinde, the invention whereof is aſcribed to <hi>Zoroaſtres</hi> the King of the <hi>Bactrians,</hi> who wrote much thereof, I muſt rather refer it to the invention of the Devil, for no man could have invented ſo much miſchief, who had not the Devil for his Tutour; for theſe works do far exceed humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as appears in the Canon Law, 26 <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>cap. Qui ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Salvatore,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>hoec vanitas magicarum artium ex <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ione malorum Angelorum in toto orbe terrarum plurimis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>luit.</hi> Therefore I am of opinion, that <hi>Zoroaſtres</hi> is ſaid to be the firſt inventour of thoſe Arts, not in a ſtrict ſenſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he firſt found them out, but becauſe he firſt received
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151237:6"/> them by tradition from the Devil, and committed them to writing, and taught them to other men, ſo that I am none of thoſe who deny Witches or Witchcraft, but of the number of thoſe who make the Devil the authour of all Witchcraft and Faſcinations. And though the ſeveral Laws of the Code, under this title, <hi>De Maleficis &amp; Mathematicis,</hi> are conceived onely in the maſculine Gender, I conceive they are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto, and do comprehend the feminine Gender. For it is a rule in that Law, and, as I take it, in Divinity alſo, that a maſculine pronounced in a matter i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> different to man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, doth comprehend the feminine, <hi>ff. De verborum ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi> So that I ſhall grant, that there are women of that Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Art; for though the ſaid Law of the Code doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſuch perſons in the maſculine Gender, yet I obſerve, that the <hi>Gloſſaries,</hi> and moſt Authours who have written on that Subject, do ſpeak moſt of all in the feminine Gender, not becauſe the feminine, contrary to the fore-mentioned Law, doth comprehend the maſculine, but becauſe theſe Arts are oftener found in the practice of women then of men, which ſome argue from the enſuing reaſons;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Women having leſs experience and learning then men, are more prone to believe, whereby they are more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceived, according to that <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>te ſaying, <hi>Quoe facile credit, facile decipitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Women abound in curioſity, and deſire the knowledge of ſuch things as leaſt appertain to them; and it is well known, that curioſity is a great diſpoſition to Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Witchcraft. And, foraſmuch as, this, for the moſt part, is the more ſimple ſex, the Devil often deceives them, <hi>ſub ſpecie recti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Women are of the ſofter complexion, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them the more eaſie to take impreſſion from evil ſpirits; and, even as when, they are inſtructed and governed by good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151237:7"/> ſpirits, they become great examples of virtue and devotion: ſo when they yield to the ſuggeſtions of the Devil, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the worſt of creatures; for, <hi>Non eſt malitia ſuper nequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lae mulieris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The frailty of woman is greater then that of man; wherefore the Devil, even in the beginning, laid ſiege to <hi>Eve,</hi> and drew her to ſin</p>
            <p>Fifthly, This ſex entertaining diſlike or hatred againſt any perſons, ſwells higher in exceſs of anger, with ſharper reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of revenge, then ordinarily men do, but being weak in power. And, foraſmuch as, <hi>Vana est ſine viribus ira,</hi> the Devil having obtained ſo fair an advantage, offers opportunities of revenge, and promiſeth the help of his aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Many women are puſilanimous, and when they fall into fits of ſadneſs and diſaſterous diſtractions, they know not well how to free themſelves from that ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore many times remain ſo long therein, untill the Devil may have the advantage of time to tempt and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Illiterate women are, for the moſt part, given to too much tatling; and therefore if they have learn't any evil Arts, they are apt to reveal them to their Conſorts, and can eaſily perſwade them ro deſire the like knowledge.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, that I have made a modeſt and induſtrious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition into the ſecrets of Nature, but herein I laboured more to humble my ſelf by ſublime ſpeculations, then to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie a vain and pernicious curioſity; for which reaſon, though I have addreſſed my painful ſtudies to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many ancient and modern Philoſophers, yet I never had the courage to addict my ſelf ſo much as to judicial Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, though in it ſelf lawful, leaſt it ſhould creare in me a deſire to draw back the impenetrable veil, which hangs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and forbidden Knowledge; for the Caſuiſts which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151237:7"/> I have read, for the right information and due regulation of my Conſcience, have ſufficiently inſtructed me of the danger that may enſue therefrom, much leſs then would I conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the beggarly Art of Witchcraft, which is altogether unlawful. By what hath been ſaid it appears, that I confeſs there are Witches, that the invention of Magick and Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft are truly aſcribed to the Devil, that there are women-Witches (I might have added, that ſome one or more of my Adverſaries, either are skill'd in that helliſh Art, or at leaſt have made uſe of thoſe who exerciſed and profeſſed the like Trade. I could alſo relate the curious Queſtions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Anſwers that have been given by the Profeſſours of that Art, to one or more of that Siſterhood) and that they, for the reaſons above rehearſed, do exceed the number of men who exerciſe that Diabolical Art. But for my ſelf, I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny that I did ever exerciſe, or know any thing of Witchcraft; nor can any of my Actions (though perhaps far tranſcending the capacity of thoſe Ladies to comprehend the motives and force of them) with any colourable reaſon render me in the leaſt ſuſpected thereof; nor have they, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they alledge any proof thereof, inſomuch, that this calumny is ſo far from being believed on the evidence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that it wants the recommendation of probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But if the great ſignes of Witches be to have no meaſure of their hatred, nor no end of their malice, which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſends ignorant women, (and ſuch are moſt of that Siſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) to revenge, which makes them often conſult with the Devil, who perſwades them upon ſuch occaſions to be Witches. Who then are more in reaſon to be ſuſpected of Witchcraft, they, who with infinite hatred, and the long continued <hi>ſeries</hi> of a moſt malicious proſecution, ariſing from no known cauſe or provocation by me given unto them, nor any concernment of theirs in the late debate of things
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151237:8"/> have afflicted me inceſſantly; or I, who in this affliction have uſed no other guard againſt them, then innocency, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and my daily prayers to Almighty God, to right me, and pardon them, as knowing, that a ſanctified affliction is better then triumphing impiety, and that innocency is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beſt, though ſometimes unſafe; as alſo that the tears of my undeſerved affliction, will in the end prove ſweeter then the immerited Trophies of their barbarous and unheard of revenge, proſecuted by ſuch means as were never uſed before, by women of quality or prudence, inſomuch, that all they, who have been verſed in thoſe rules, which may ſerve to conduct us through the practical intercourſes of this life, ſtand amazed, as being unable to parallel them out of the Hiſtories of meer <hi>Scythiàns</hi> and <hi>Barbarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, It is ordinary with Negromancers and Witches to raiſe illuſions and phantaſms inſtead of realities: So <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius</hi> made <hi>Achilles</hi> appear in his Tent twelve foot high. <hi>Bantabaremus</hi> ſheweth to <hi>Baſilius</hi> the ſoul of his ſon <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantine, lamlicus</hi> made to appear in <hi>Syrta</hi> two figures of little children like <hi>Cupids,</hi> all which had nothing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, but were meer <hi>Spectres.</hi> Even ſo theſe Ladies are not onely content to corrupt ſome truths with many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious prevarications, but repreſent things altogether falſe under the colour of truth, which is the more dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicle <hi>Spectre,</hi> by how much the more it tendeth to wrong an innocent Stranger; nay, theſe Ladies, for proof of their skill, endeavour to repreſent that as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which contradicts common ſenſe, as will appear by that, which is the matter of my next enquity, into the reaſons wherefore, and the means whereby I ſhould be thought to have exerciſed Witchcraft, to work out ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of mine on the above-mentioned Perſon.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151237:8"/>
            <p>It cannot be thought that I ſhould uſe Witchcraft to create an affection in him towards me, or to increaſe it; for it is well known, that almoſt at our firſt interview, even before I could well paſs the formalities of beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Witch, we had a high eſteem and affection for one another, and ſettled upon ſuch ſolid grounds of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that they are as unalterable as they are unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>Nor can it be ſuppoſed, that I ſhould endeavour to ſqueeze out of him any part of his goods or eſtate by Witchcraft, or other baſe means, much below me to think of; I ſhould rather, had I that Art, uſe it to thoſe who have greater eſtates, and leſs Charge to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. What other ends I could have to bewitch one I honour ſo much, others may gueſs. But I know not.</p>
            <p>As for the means uſed to bewitch him, I hear no other alledged, then my giving him a Ring with a <hi>Greek</hi> Poſie in it. Firſt, I anſwer, as in the preſence of God, That I never knew that he had a Ring with a <hi>Greek</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Secondly, That I never gave him any Ring at all.</p>
            <p>In the next place, It is as groundleſly reported by ſome of thoſe Ladies, as it was maliciouſly invented by others of them, That I am a common Liar, which were it a true allegation, it might eaſily be proved, becauſe things that are common, are more clearly and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved. But I am ſo well known to all thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality who converſe with me (who onely are competent Witneſſes in ſuch a Caſe) that I am not guilt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty hereof, that I may ſay to the loudeſt Reporter of that untruth. What was given in anſwer by <hi>Libanius</hi> to <hi>Telemachus</hi> upon the like occaſion, <hi>Velim ego apud to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151237:9"/> mendax eſſe, dum caeteri te mendacem eſſe dicere deſinant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to gratifie them by yielding ſo much as I can in this particular, I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs, That this their imputation onely wants truth to convince me of being a Liar. Again, So conſcienciouſly have I alwayes conformed my ſelf to the ſpeaking of truth without equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, or mental reſervation, and ſhall alwayes ſo continue to do the like, that, as I had rather theſe few Leaves were an unwritten Blank then a rude Defence; ſo alſo that it were an abſolute Confeſſion of Guilt, then a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Apology.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſuffice in anſwer to this Objection, until my Adverſaries ſhall inſtance in any one untruth that they ever heard proceed from my Lips; and if it ſhall be thought that I have in this, or any other particular part of my Anſwer, ſaid too much againſt thoſe Ladies, I wiſh I could have ſaid no more, though it be a great ſatisfaction that one of them, who formerly lifted up her voice like a Trumpet, with loudeſt exclamation againſt me, is, by denying what ſhe had ſaid falſly of me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a double liar.</p>
            <p>But no more of exaggeration againſt them in this or any other particular; for my chiefeſt aim, Gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is my own inoffenſive defence; for which reaſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, though I want neither information, power, opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor ſharp provocations, I have not, not ſhall I in the whole Contexture of this Book, either cauſleſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject any thing againſt them, or wrongfully detract from them, as they have done from me, but ſhall onely call them down as baſe moneys to their true value, nor will I give them any new ſtamp of impreſſion, for the Im<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Superſcription which they now bear in the Worlds
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151237:9"/> eſtimation, ſufficiently notifie them to be what they are, not onely injurious to me, but alſo as blames<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for many other things, not mentioned here, as they are mainly culpable of ſeveral of thoſe things which they have falſly objected againſt me. If theſe Ladies, in the exerciſe of their late aſſumed authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, had regulated their behaviour in this matter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the advice and example of a Noble Lady, who did not think fit to countenance their aſſembly with her continual preſence, their paſſions would have moved according to the ſevere allowance of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedce, gravity, and piety, and the due proportions of provocation given to, or apprehended by them, and they would have vented themſelves by the ſealed meaſures of right reaſon; but not ſubmitting to that regulation, they are become, in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Phraſe, <hi>Ieugo de muchachos,</hi> a laughing-ſtock of Children. And their actions, relating to me, have not been warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any one particular by any Principle of Piety, Rule of Charity, Moderation, Learning, Prodence, or Maxim of Policy; if they had had a regard to Prudence and Policy, they would not have intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this matter farther then the proportion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern they had therein; for, <hi>Culpa est immiſcere ſe rei ad ſe non pertinenti.</hi> If they had been tempered by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they would not have managed a buſineſs of ſo little concernment, extending no farther then to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, with as much vigour of debate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, as if the entire intereſt and propriety of the three Nations had been concerned in the debate: if they had been skilled in Argumentation, they would not have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151237:10"/> laboured to infer immediate conſequences from far fetcht ſurmiſes, ungrounded rumours, and peeviſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitions, they would not have repreſented that for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which contradicts common ſenſe; they would not have ſcrued up every light and temerary ſuſpition to the height of a violent preſumption; nor would they have thought, that their own bare reports were to be believed on the credit of their proper Teſt, without farther enquiry and examination they would not have concluded, becauſe I was civil to a Perſon of merit and civility, that therefore I had ſubmitted to unchaſte embraces, as if every civil friend muſt needs be a partner in ſin; or that becauſe that Perſon commended the liberality of Nature and Art, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing on me many gifts and endowments which they wanted, that therefore I was deſtitute of modeſty, and He guilty of a ſinful Converſe with me. I give but a touch of this matter here, becauſe I have refet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to the more ſecure and prudent management of my Council, who will proſecute it with effect in the Archbiſhop's Conſiſtory, who may eaſily make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that they ought to be chaſtized with the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Rods of Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline; for, injured re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, <hi>in re gravi,</hi> requires a reparation as publick, as the injury is notorious. In the m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an time it is well known to thoſe who converſe with me, that though I be young, and in the verdure of my Age, I am none of thoſe who ſport themſelves in the green ways of fading Pleaſures, but exerciſe my ſelf painfully, and with no ſmall aſperities, in thoſe ſtudies, which may facilitate my progreſs to the chief of my aims, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151237:10"/> is the Kingdom of Heaven; and I have alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Garland of a Marital Chaſtity, before all glittering favours which can poſſibly flow from the glorious circle of the brighteſt Imperial Diadem on Earth; nay, I had rather enjoy that virtue, then to be crown'd with the Royal State, and Imperial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of all the Kingdoms upon Earth. Nay farther, I had rather, were it not for the Conjugal ſtate of life, whereunto I am bound by the Ordinance of God, withdraw my ſelf into the receſs of a Religious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement, then converſe with any man whoſoever he be; nay, I had rather live chaſtly and innocently in the loweſt and darkeſt dungeon of a melancholy retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then I would conſent to the leaſt propoſal of any immodeſt deſire. Laſtly, I had rather die a ſpeedy death, then to continue or prolong life with any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, which may ſpread it ſelf with a diffuſive ſtain, to the leaſt diſparagement of thoſe Illuſtrious Families from which I have deſcended, or whereunto I have the Honour to be related; for which reaſons, and for my own Vindication, I have directed a legal procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt them for the clearing of my Reputation, which though moſt tender, will bear a Tryal before ſo indifferent and learned a Iudge as is the Archbiſhop, or his Chancellour. Some things, I know, are ſo tender in their own nature, as if they be once fulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they are hardly capable of waſhing: as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Garden Envi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which, as <hi>Avicenna</hi> ſaith, loſeth its virtue in waſhing; and therefore he ſaith in the words of his Latine Tranſlation, <hi>Interdictum est ab ablutione ejus lege &amp; medicina.</hi> But though the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151237:11"/> of a Lady be tender in its ſelf, and requires ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nice rules and inſtructions for its Vindication. I ſhall, with very much confidence, rely on the Iudges and Advocates for the management, of my Defence, and the clearing of my Reputation, which will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhrink, nor loſe its virtue in the waſhing.</p>
            <p>But to return from whence I have a little digreſſed, I muſt needs ſay, That if I had been guilty of ſome of thoſe enormities above-mentioned, it was no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their prudence to urge them publickly againſt me; for if their memories had been ſo officious to them, as to retain a repreſentation of what they have done themſelves, and whereof they are guilty, they would wiſely have ſpared me for at leaſt ſome of their own ſakes; much leſs doth it become them, whoſe roofs are covered with brittle Glaſs, to throw ſtones at the more ſolid covering of their Neighbours houſes; for ſuch is the prudent Advertiſement of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>El que biene teiados de vidro no tire piedra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, al de tu vezino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, They have not carried themſelves after the manner of Chriſtian Charity towards me, nor accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the duty of their own Conſcience; for that would have required, that they ſhould firſt have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to me, with a deſire to have received ſatisfaction, before they had publiſhed any thing againſt me, at leaſt, without proof, to my prejudice. Secondly, They have been uncharitable to themſelves, in that they have, by their courſe of proceedings againſt me, caught others a facil way and method of injuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for, as <hi>Ordinata Charitas incipit à ſeipſa:</hi> ſo doth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151237:11"/> uncharitableneſs many times end in it ſelf: and theſe Ladies may be aſſured, that as <hi>Tyrus</hi> had not long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced at the miſery of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when the ſame mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery came upon her ſelf. So this injury which they have done to me, if it be not puniſh't in them, it will, as well by example as merit, bring on them the like affliction, which hitherto I have ſo ſadly born, hereof I know they will become ſenſible here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after (though their Conſcience be now ſealed up with ſlumber and obduration) when the eye of their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (now dimm'd with foggy miſts, riſing from their tumultuous and fiery paſſions, ſhall behold my clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed innocency cloathed with the brightneſs of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er glory (foe true metal will prove the brighter for rubbing) then will they wiſh that they had been checkt by the reins of a ſober and religions reſtraint, ſo as to have kept within the bounds of Truth, and that they had followed a leſs paſſionate, and more reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courſe againſt me; for; without peradventure, when they ſhall be returned to their more ſettled thoughts, they will be of another mind, and heartily deſire that they had never endeavoured, out of unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved malice, either to mu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fle up the face of Truth in the obſcurity of a black Bag, or to fit things to their malicious deſires, and deſtructive deſigns, by turning truth into lies, as hitherto they have done, wish a too bare-faced confidence, having caſt off from their front the comely veil of due modeſty; for ſuch hath been their carriage hitherto towards me, that if I ſhould have repreſented in my actions and deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the abſolute portra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cture of <hi>Aristotle</hi>'s moral <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151237:12"/> or ſhould I have lived in as ſtrict a regularity as a <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> or could my courſe of life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have entituled me to a Rubrick in the Kalendar, or juſtified the painting of me with rayes, yet they would have figured no better thoughts of me, then they ought to have of themſelves, they would have cenſured me as extremely vitious; for deflexion from, and diſſimilitude to virtue, are the fierceſt cenſurers of the virtuous, and will draw all their actions into the worſt interpretations. It hath been ſaid, I know not how truly, of the <hi>Belgick</hi> Inquiſitours, that they did confeſs, when they met with any of the Ancients, ſpeaking otherwiſe then the Church, <hi>Quovis Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> they uſed any ſhift to remedy it; and although theſe Ladies want ingenuity to confeſs the figments and prevarications which they have uſed to make me ſeem otherwiſe in my words and actions, then truth can warrant them to report of me; yet, thanks be to God, I am happy in this, that he hath placed me in the Noble City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> inhabited by very many pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and truly Noble Perſons of both ſexes, who have obſerved my deportment, and are not unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Maskaries theſe Ladies have uſed againſt me in their late Earie-like Scenes, wherein they would have repreſented me to the eye of the World, in the falſe dreſs of their malicious impoſitions. It hath been long ſince ſaid of Stage-players, that they are many times high in applauſe, but poor in reputation. Theſe Actrices, perhaps in their firſt Scenes, found ſome applauſe amongſt themſelves, but the World knows they have not mended their own reputations, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151237:12"/> to deſtroy mine; and it now appears in great viſibility to every underſtanding perſon, that though they have wounded their own conſciences to ſtain my reputation, their wounds will not be ſo ſoon cured, as my reputation cleared. Wherefore I do ſo much pity them, as that I deſire they may eſcape the Satyrical Whip of Poets and Lampoons, and that they may be freed from the Strapadoes of an evil Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by uſing the due remedies preſcribed by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts, which are Retractation, Compenſation, and a lowly penitent dejection of mind before God, which if they forbear to perform, they will not onely ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves hereafter hateful to their own imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, but alſo lyable to be caſt headlong to the loweſt and moſt painful tormentory of hell, which I pray God to prevent in his mercy, by giving them a ſight and true ſenſe of their ſins, and thereby to put a ſeaſonable ſtop to the fury of their malicious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt me; for if their own awakened pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence cannot bring them to theſe ſentiments, yet I am well aſſured it is poſſible, that the Omnipotent Lord of Heaven and Earth, who made the Sun, that mighty Creature, the Prince of all the Lights in Heaven, to ſtop and ſtand ſtill in the rapid Career of its greateſt velocity, can in an inſtant prohibit their cauſleſs proſecution againſt me, or render it vain, and of no effect; and that the ſame God, who made the impetuous Current of the raging Sea to recoil, and the mercileſs flame of devouring fire to become a ſoft refreſhing air, can ſo temper the rage of theſe tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladies, as to make them immediately pull in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151237:13"/> their horns, and blunt their ſtings, otherwiſe, at leaſt, when their immortal fouls ſhall be ſummoned by grim Death to diflodge from their tottering tabernacles of cold clay, and ſhall begin to enter into the diſputed Confines of Eternity, then will they wiſh that they had been as free from injuring me by their Calumny, as I am innocent of the matters they falſly lay to my charge.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not at this time ſay much more to theſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, I ſhall therefore diſmiſs them with a few Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that though they have all been cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, yet I do not think that they have been equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cruel to me, notwithſtanding which, I ſhall ſay, that every one of them hath been too cruel; for it is obſerved, that the moſt tame of Tygers is a cruel beaſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I obſerve, that thoſe Ladies who were interwoven in the Contexture of ſo ſtrong a Faction againſt me, are not the onely perſons who have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured me, for they who have excited them to detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction are not without ſin, nay perhaps more guilty; for <hi>Malletus</hi> the Caſuiſt ſaith, Theſe do not onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, as the Detractour, <hi>effectu detractionis;</hi> but alſo are unto others <hi>cauſà detrahendi.</hi> Nay, the Detractour is but the Authour of his own ſin, but theſe are Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of their own and others: for which cauſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth another Caſuiſt, <hi>Tenetur ad restitutionem, niſi De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractor ipſe restituat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whoſoever hath delighted himſelf in hearing detractions, though, as the Caſuiſts ſay, he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151237:13"/> doth not offend <hi>contra justitiam,</hi> becauſe he is not <hi>efficax cauſa damni;</hi> yet he offends againſt charity, for that he takes pleaſure <hi>malo Proximi,</hi> which cannot ſtand with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Superiours in Government, who do not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Detractors, do not onely ſin againſt charity, but alſo againſt juſtice, <hi>Cum Obligatione restituendi ſi ſubditus, non restituat.</hi> ſo ſay <hi>Leſsius Reginaldus,</hi> and <hi>Molina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Parents, Husbands, and Maſters, who have ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently heard their Children, Wives, or Servants detract from any one, though without delectation, are guilty of a moral incitation to detraction; for, <hi>Qui tacet, conſentire videtur:</hi> and <hi>Fernandes</hi> gives two reaſons for this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Tum quia non impedit malum Proximi, tum quia non emendat errantem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, They who have defamed any one by detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are bound to reſtitution, not onely where the party had a poſitive good fame, <hi>i. e. bene audiebat,</hi> and therefore did ſuffer the loſs <hi>boni ceſsant<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> but alſo where the party had but a negative good name, <hi>i. e. non male an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ichat,</hi> and therefore ſuffers an immergent loſs, by poſitive infamy brought upon him; but eſpecially in the former caſe, wherein I have been ſo highly injured.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Reſtitution is not always made according to the quality of the offence before God, but proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the infamy ariſing therefrom; and therefore he who divulgeth a true crime to the defamation of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſhall make equal reſtitution with him who objected or impoſed a falſe one; wherefore <hi>Fernandes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitas reſtitutionis non oritur ex aequalitate culpae, ſed ex aequ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate damni.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151237:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151237:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151237:15"/>
            <p>Eighthly, Though <hi>Tolet</hi> be of opinion, That where a good fame is not to be reſtored <hi>in proprio genere</hi> by retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, it is not to be reſtored by way of another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation: and though he enforceth his opinion from this conſideration, That as life, ſo a good fame is not <hi>pretio aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabilis,</hi> and therefore cannot be proportioned to any eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. I ſhall hold the oppoſite opinion, maintained by the Angelical and ſubtil Doctors <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and <hi>Scotus Thom. q.</hi> 32. <hi>ar.</hi> 2. <hi>Scot. in</hi> 4. <hi>d.</hi> 15. 9 4. as alſo by <hi>Soto</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>art.</hi> 3. who ſay, That though life as well as a good fame do entitatively and eſſentially exceed any price, yet in reſpect to she eſtimation of men, they may be reduced to a certain value: and I have read, that it is held to be the common opinion of School-Divines, that <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do debitum compenſari nequit, ad aequalitatem in eodem genere compenſandum est in al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, quoad fieri poteſt compenſando,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am afraid that I have held the Courteous Reader too long in the thorny terms of Caſuiſtical and School-Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; yet becauſe it is neceſſary to cure my Adverſaries, not onely by a prick of reprehenſion, but alſo by ſtirring up their Conſciences by ſome pungent incitations to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and ſatisfaction, I hope to be excuſed, and the rather, for that I ſhall lead the Readers patience by a mor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eaſie and ſhort way to a Concluſion, having but one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration more to ſubjoyn, which is this.</p>
            <p>If the private diſlike of ſo many Ladies, fomented by envy, after ſo many ſpies ſet on my behaviour, and ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous an inquiſition had againſt me, and having a voraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will to deſtroy my Credit, cannot find any evidence to convince me of any thing ſcandalous, it is no ſlight Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of my Innocency. If all their endeavours againſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151237:15"/> me met together, as the beams of the Sun, on a burning-glaſs cannot kindle a fire to my deſtruction, their moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent attempts proving as the Rayes under the meridian which cannot produce a flame by reflection on a burning-glaſs, for want of ſolid matter to work on. I hope the Reader will free me from all Attachments of buſie ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the future, and that no man will own a neceſſity of believing ſuggeſtions upon the reputation of their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing me hereafter, for the reputation of ſuch people as are found falſe accuſers, or like an <hi>Iriſh</hi> pair of Tongs, which grow ſhorter in the uſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with a ſtedfaſt Declaration of a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded hope, which is, that all Perſons of Quality of both ſexes in this City, which is the Metropolis of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty as well as preheminency, will compaſſionate my inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red innocency, hitherto groaning under the inſolency of <hi>ſhe</hi>-cruelty and oppreſſion, trampled upon, as it were, to duſt, by the barbarous feet of pride and unwomanly inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; but that which begets in me my moſt ſecure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, is that of <hi>Ioh, Behold now, my Witneſs is in heaven, and my record is on high,</hi> whereunto appealeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Frances Plunkett.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>P. 14. lege <hi>Syria.</hi> p. 19. l. <hi>Endive.</hi> p. 21.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151237:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
